Okay, and let's go to second,
let's go to multimedia programming,
okay?  And let's see,
we have engines, okay?  We have in areas
of spatialization, okay?  Libraries and
programming languages.  Today I want to
teach a class that I think you're going to
really like, eh, because up until
now we've been working
in 2D, okay?  But of course, making
video games also includes making
3D video games.
So what happens?  Well, in 2D
we can work dryly, we can
work raw, right?  But in 3D
things change a lot.
So, from
here on, for example, on the
topic of Let's see, let's see.  Ah, ah, oh, oh,
oh, the trick.  Okay, wait, wait,
Fran, let's start there.  Let's
start there.  Wait, because this is how I'll
tell you.  Okay, well, I
had forgotten.  Fran, you see, eh,
a trick,
eh, JS.Hht.  HTML.
You see, for years, for years, I
was a big fan, I was a big fan of the
JQuery library because for years,
before JavaScript came into play, in
the progress it has been making since
2015, well, JQuery was amazing for
writing code.  So to do
things, you would put, for example,
function point selector, right?  and
you did it and this selector
took away from having to do uh having to
do pure JavaScript, right?  And it
took away the one about doing the document query
selector, I don't know what, I don't know how many.
Well, the other day, the other day
when I was doing the salmon thing and
obviously I was doing it with the
help of artificial intelligence,
suddenly, suddenly I'm going to show it to you,
suddenly in Salmon, now you'll see, eh,
where are you?
Oh, Salmon.  Okay, I come here to
index.html, HTML.  I get off here,
I get off here and I start to see.  Now
you'll see.
Oh no, he'll have taken it away from me now.
Wait.
Dollar.
One moment.
Yes, but
damn.  I don't
see that he has taken it from me.  I see here,
here, here, here.  I see this here.
And I was like, okay, I mean, the
first thing I thought, this here is
pure jQuery syntax, okay?
And I said, what is this, I mean, how come he
put JQuery on me when it's a
library that I've been using and will use a
million times?  I have a
lot of affection for him, okay?  But it's an
outdated bookstore.  Yeah, I mean, I don't teach it in class anymore.
I'd like to, but I teach you what
's coming in the future, not what's
dying from the past.  And then I said,
wow, how is it that Char GPT is
doing a new development for me with JQ
Query?  And then I went upstairs, okay?
I went up and said, I don't see jQuery
imported anywhere.  I made a
jQuery F control and said, "But if there's no
jQuery, how come it's using
jQuery syntax?"  And then, and
then I went down here,
started going through the code, went
down here, here it is,
bam,
okay?  and I saw that there and that line
there is the one that we use to use
selectors with document query selector.
So the trick is to copy
that line and do the following.  Doc type
HTML HTML HTML.   I'm
telling you, I was totally amazed.
Okay.  Yes, it's not that it's
actually a function, but just a
moment, and I say just a moment because Ramón
and Luis won't see my screen, that
is, they'll be hearing me, but they won't
see my screen, so I'm going to
unshare and share again.
So Luis and Ramón, please confirm via
chat. I should be able to hear you, but we're having a
problem with your microphone, okay?
So, uh, tell me via chat and
I'll take this microphone issue into account
to solve it in the next
class.  Well, from now until the next
class, I mean.  Please confirm that you
can see me correctly now.  Good.  And
then I go to body.  I go to body and
in body I put script
and then I put script and then I
use the arrow operator, okay?  Which
is the short form of declaring
functions within JavaScript.
Perfect, phenomenal.  And so that
means that this whole document
query selector S is summarized in the
dollar function that accepts the S parameter. Okay?
This is the name of the function and this is
parameter S. So, if I now
come here and say div id container,
I now come here and say dollar
container
pun text content is or is equal to hello
and that's it.  I mean, the idea is that you
declare that this is really what
the JQuery library did back in the day,
so it's really reinventing the
wheel, right?  But you declare
this simple line at the top, and from
there, throughout the entire bottom section, you can
use the dollar as a selector, and that's it
.  Because this is also a query
selector.  The cool thing about JQuery back in the
day was that the dollar has an S and
the S is for selector, so I select
the container and add the text content
hello
and that's it.  That's the question.  Just a
moment, I have audio blocked here.
Okay.  Okay.  Now, uh, so nothing,
this was the great trick, but it's not a great trick
precisely because it has a lot of
code, quite the opposite, but it
's a great trick because with one line you
'll save yourself from writing a
lot of code later on.  Okay?  That was
kind of the idea.  Well, I was
telling you, I was telling you that let's
see, I
come this way, I come this way, I
come this way and then obviously,
Fran, as it is as you are commenting,
this is part of what at the time
was the JQuery library, which was nothing more and nothing
less than a collection of functions
and methods that were based on
JavaScript, but served to write
less JavaScript.  Okay.  Hey, Ramón, I see
you've just left and just come in.  Okay,
if you don't see my screen when you log in now
, let me know and I'll restart
screen sharing.  Okay?
So, let's see.  We're going here to
DAM 2526.
I'm going to second, I'm going to multimedia.
Okay.  And I told you about multimedia, I told you
that in engines Perfect, perfect.  In terms of
engines, let's see, here in the
areas of specialization I don't plan on
teaching you 3D straight up because 3D
straight up is sometimes enough to make you slit your
wrists.  I mean, a lot of people say, "No, it's
like 2D, but with one more dimension,
right? Okay, 3D programming, believe me, I
can tell you, it's
bloody amazing."  So, just as
you already know, you already
know me, that I don't like to use
frameworks or libraries as much as possible
,
in the case of creating
3D video games, we have no choice
but to use libraries.  We're going to do
a demonstration
and for that I'm going to show you
a library called A Frame.  We're going to
work with two
standard libraries: the A Frame library, which is
super easy, simple, and incredibly cool
, and the 3JS library, which isn't as
simple, but offers more control.  So for
this, for this I'm going to, look, I'm going to
go to Ostia for a moment, what do I have
this here for?  Here.
Okay.  And okay.
So, uh, I'm going here, I'm
going to aframe.
Okay, in this Frame library I'm going to
do a hello webr.  Okay, and let's see
the source, let's see the code.
Momentin.
Oh, how glitchy he is.  Okay.
And I don't know if it is
here
.  Okay.  And viewers.
Ah, page not found.  Okay, fantastic.
Let's see.
Yes, but no.  Okay, this is it if I don't get it
from my notes from last year.  But let's
see,
okay, this is it.  Just a moment.  This is what
we are seeing on the screen, but
I want you to see.  It's that view source
should give me
the
view source code,
not editor for remixes,
if not I go to documentation and if not,
as I said, I
get it from last year.
samples is not fried.
Okay, let's get to the documentation.
Let's see.  Get started.
This is this is.  Okay, that's it.  That's
enough for me.  002 aframe.  That is,
iioo html.
Okay.  And what it basically does is the
following.  And ah, wait, wait, wait.
Ramón, you say that ah, Luis sees the
screen, but Ramón doesn't see the screen.
Okay, okay.  Okay.  Sorry.  Okay, here and the
whole screen and screen one.  And now,
first of all, Ramón, you should see the
screen.  Let me know, confirm.
Now yes.  Perfect.  Okay, so what do
we have?  Okay, everyone pay attention
to the screen because we're going to start
freaking out.  I have
14 lines of code, okay?  Less
than 15 lines of code, I
obviously have the line that does the
magic, which is this one, okay?  It is the
loading of the aframe.minmin.js library.
And from there the library adds
support.  for a series of
custom labels that obviously have to
be under the nomenclature
of this object, that is, the
library.  First, we create a
3D scene.
And once we create a 3D scene,
we're going to go little by little,
003, little by little,
what I'm going to do is create, you know what?
a sphere.
A sphere, I take it all off
and let's go there.  So I come here,
I go to local host
and I go to DAM 2526,
I go to multimedia, I go to analysis,
I go to specialization, I go to
exercises, I go to little by little and here we
have it.  Okay, so what we have here is
a ball.  It is a ball that is in
position and now the cod starts, in
position X0
Y 1.25
Z - 5. What does that mean?  Well, this
means that in 3D space this
is the X, this is the Y, the depth is
the Z. So, if the object
were not at -5, the problem is that it
would be stuck to the camera, right?
I was inside the chamber.  The idea is
that we put -5 precisely because the
camera is at zero so that the object
is further away, right?  be deeper
down.
Next we can modify the
radius,
a smaller sphere,
a larger sphere and a much
larger sphere.
And then we can modify the
color.  Why do I like this bookstore?
Because doing this in web GL is a
nightmare because you have to program
the polygons by hand.  While with
this library, everything is automated and
you simply create a tag on top of it
, you don't even create JavaScript at the moment,
and based on that tag,
you create FF00 color code.
I want it to be a red sphere.  Now
I want it to be 00 FF00.  I want a
green sphere.  And now I want a
blue sphere.  00 FF.  So I come over here and
blue sphere.
Okay, next, FF FF00, okay?
A yellow sphere.  Next,
as you saw before, I
can create more objects, so 004.
Now I add a box,
so I have
an object called box,
so it's fierce, but of course, x - 1.
What for?  Well, to move the box a
little to one side.  So I do this.
Now I add a box and I have a
box there.  Let's put the two boxes, that
is, the two objects at 1.25.
Okay, there so that both are at the
same height.  And then, obviously, I
can also add a floor
005. Now I create a plan for a floor.
Good.  So so let's see.  Now
I add a plan,
okay?  where I say 00 -4, rotation
-90, width and height I'm going to put 8 and 8,
okay?  And I color.  Now I add a plane and
it's a little too low, okay?
Then you can go up, obviously.
And this is a frame, okay?  Imagine the
wonders that can be done with
this.  I insist, from the point of view of
the relationship between I give you, you give me.  That is
, notice that we put in a
minimal set of resources and what
we get is a super cool result.
Obviously, you
can do wonders by
placing objects, but working with
primitives and positioning primitives
straight away can be a bit difficult.
So, we have to admit that the
point of all this is to bring
geometry modeled in other programs.
Me, for example, in this case, let's see it
.
I'm going to open my
desktop and bring Blender.   It
can be modeled with any program.
Blender.  Here is Blender 5.
I'm going to open Blender.
It has opened on the other screen for me.
Okay, e Blender,
e Blender has the following, add mes el
monkey, okay?
So I have a monkey and now
what I'm going to do next is
export it.  Let's say Blender is a
program that serves as a
3D modeler, not only because it just made
a monkey head, but because the idea
is that in Blender I can do whatever
I want, right?  So I do this and
move on to the next thing.  Sorry, let's see, I'll
save it first.
I'm going to root, I'm going to bar, I'm going to W,
I'm going to HTML, I'm going to, let's
see, I'm going to DAM, I'm
going to second, I'm going to multimedia, I'm
going to analysis, I'm going to areas, I'm
going to contain new exercises, okay?
and I put here eh susan, because the
Blender monkey is called Susan.
But
now what I'm going to do next
is export it in a format that is
compatible with a frame.  So I'm going to
export, I'm going to GLTF, it's the
supported format,
I'm going to take a GLB, for example, and I
say susan.glb,
okay?  I export, sorry.  There is no
material to make it look correct.   It
has to have a material, even if it's
white, but it has to have a
material.  So I save,
export,
GLTF,
Susan, okay?  And there we have it.  Good.
So now I come
here 006, I
load a GLB, GLB or GLTF.
Okay, I'm coming this way.  Since
the repositories or
official documentation aren't working for me, I'm going to say,
eh, the GLB.
Let's see.
Okay.
Okay.  This is the question.
If you want, if you want, I'll even
bring just the GLB,
okay?  Only the GLB.
And then
first of all, I load the model, I
call it like susan.glb GLB
and once I've loaded it, now I
use it and I tell it the GLTF model is
model and from there its
position is this and its scale is this and
its rotation is this and whatever.  Okay?
So now next
I come over here,
I come over here, I'm going to charge a GLB
and here we have it.  Okay, just a moment
because okay, I have the look controls.
Okay, I'm going to take off the look.
Okay.  Ah, very good.  Hey, let's see.
Wait, what did I have before
and no, there is no camera.  Okay, okay, that's
the problem.  I take away the camera.  Now
we'll put a camera, okay?  And surcharge.
Now yes.  Okay, and look how I can
open the model, I can go into the
model, I can, okay,
take the model, I can open it and I can
do whatever I want, I can,
okay?  Being out there working with the
model and all that.  Okay, so next,
we're going to see that there are
different ways in which we can
work.  Now we'll talk about
materials, we'll talk a little bit about
cameras.  To talk about cameras,
let's see that a moment ago we had
the look controls.  Let's see
that there is one thing that is the orbit
controls.  Add orbit controls.
We're going to come over here and say 007
orbit controls.
Okay.  And we will create a camera.  That is.
Okay.  And the orbit controls.  Moment.
While we're at it, give me a light.  Okay.  I didn't
want to talk about a moment of enlightenment, but
well, now we're talking about enlightenment.
Okay, orbit controls
allow us to do the following.
Orbit controls.  Okay.  And just a
moment.
Wait.  No, what's going on?  Any
mistakes perhaps?  No, okay.  Okay.
Moment,
huh.
Nothing is happening.
Let's see it.
Okay,
just a moment.
Okay, let's go.
Okay.
No. Oh,
no.
What's going on?
Let's see, target 01- 2. Okay, because the
object is at 01 - 2. Okay,
no.  Let's see,
orbit not working.
Let's see.  Meanwhile, while you're
doing this, uh, I'm going to show you,
I'm going to create a kind of 3D scene,
uh, to make something like a
virtual museum.  I come here, I go to Blender
and I'm going to do something.  I'm going to create a
box.
Once I have this box,
I'm going to extrude two units.  I'm going to
extrude two units.
Once I've extruded, now
next I'm going to delete this
face, I'm
going to go ahead and
delete this face.  Okay,
once I've done this, now that I've
done it correctly.  Wait a minute, I
'm not sure.
I think I have to delete this one too
.  Okay, let's try it.  Now
I select and invert the normal ones in the month
.  It seems like nothing has happened
on the screen, but I tell you, it has
.  To now continue
joining some objects with others.
So I'm going to make a duplicate.  Broken
90 gr.  I do this.  Hey, watch out.   Let's
see, wait.
I want a grid,
I want to duplicate it, rotate it 90º,
place it.  Now yes.  Okay.  And so on.
Correct.  Very good.  Now I want to
duplicate this.
Okay.
Okay.  Okay.
Now I want
this, this, this.
Now I want to put this here
and Okay.  Okay.  And if I put that there.
Hm.  It means I put this here, I
think.
Yes, okay.  It seems to work.
And now next.
Now I don't know what to put where.
Well, you know what?  I think this is
more or less enough for me.  So now
I'm going to do it like this.
No, not this.
Let's see.  This is this.
So
I do this.
I think I
do.  No, I don't
do
that.
Okay.  And now, as you can see, I'm looking for
a certain modality.  There, there.  Very
good.  Yes, that's the idea.  Now
you see, not doing Call of Duty,
obviously, okay?
The idea is to make a map.  That's what
I'm trying to do.
Okay, now this goes here.
Okay.
And I think that more or less I think that
more or less we can launch it to see
what happens.  Okay, so there's milk.  There's
milk.  That I wanted to put some material on it.
Don't tell me.
Oh, look, you know what?  I'm going to put it
all together and add just one material and that's it
.
Okay, that's it.  Material.  Okay, now I'm
going to save this
as a map.
And once I save it as a map,
now what I'm going to do is export it.
I keep it as a map.  GLldb.
I come this way.
Hey, okay, okay, okay, okay, okay, okay, okay, okay, okay, okay
, okay, okay.  Let's
see if we can get the orbit
working.
Okay.  Wow.
Mother, what is this?
Okay.
Ah, quad clone.  No, no, it doesn't
work for me.  No, it
doesn't matter.  I'm going to do the WAS controls,
that is, being able to walk with WASD
and that's it.  Okay, so what I'm going to
do now is load up a GLB.
I'm saving this as 008 was.
And in the WAST what I'm going to do now is
load the map.glb.
Let's see it.  So I come over here,
I'm going to load map.glb,
okay?  And we're going to see it.
And I'm inside the map.
And if you notice, And if you
notice, well I'm inside the map.
Okay.
Okay.  And now I can move inside.
And the idea, what I want you to see is
how to use this library to
make a map, that is, not just make a
map because the map is actually made
within Blender, but putting it into
operation, loading it onto a
web page and creating an interactive application
is as simple as what I'm
showing you on the screen.  Okay?  Let's
continue.  Let's learn more things.
This is by default the was controls.
Okay, wait a minute.
And the orbit component,
quick fix, full example, is that I would
like to have the orbit working.
So, orbit controls.
No, no,
okay, it's okay.  Now then
we will get it from somewhere.
Let's see, let's do something,
eh, aframe.
Orbit sample with a box.
Okay, I'm going to tell him I want
a new conversation because, as you
know, when GPT chat is broken you can't
get it out of there.
Let's see.
That?
No, no, no, no, no.  Ah, Arbit.  No, no,
no, no, no, no, no.  Stop, stop, stop.
No, no, no,
no.  Sorry.  I meant
camera orbit around object.   It
seems that I told you arbitrarily
that I was talking to you about intelligence,
that is, augmented reality.
Sure,
that's it,
okay?  In this case it is not making a
real orbit, but what it is
doing is a look controls with a
rotation in a parent.  Well, okay, that
works for me.   Let's
see,
I mean, as long as it allows me to orbit,
even with a trick of parent, it
works for me.
Already.  Yes, but
okay.  But not with animation,
but with mouse control
as in orbit controls.  What I want to
understand about frame orbit controls is
this.
Let's see.  Wait,
no.
Well, today is not Orbit
Controls' day.
Well, nothing, it doesn't matter.
Let's see it.
Okay.
And orbit controls,
right?  And none of them work.
Well, whatever.  Let's talk about lights
and then we'll talk about orbit.  I'll find
some working examples.  Okay,
so let's talk about lights.  To do this I will
go little by little.
Hey 009,
let's talk about lights.
And the first thing I'm going to do is turn off
the light.  So for that what I'm going to
do is the following.  Sky Color
010. I turn off the light.   I
tell him that I'm putting a sky color on him and the
sky color is 00, that
is,
okay, black.
Okay, now I've turned off the
background, now I want to turn off the light.  So
for that I come here, I
had put a box.  I carry a GLB.
No, look, not this, obviously, look.
Okay, come on, let's get to this.
Okay, I'm going to create a light
011. Now I remove all light
and tell
entity to add an ambient light of
zero intensity.   Let's
go for it.
Okay, now you can't see anything.  And now,
once I've turned off the light, let's see
what this is.  Intensity 1, okay?  what it
does is add an ambient light.  The
ambient light, I'm going to put zero
012. The ambient light
is a fill.
The abigo 0.5, 5, for example,
the ambient light is a fill.  Once
we have fills, we also have
013, we have directional lights.
The turn signals, let's see it
here,
the turn signals are like a
sun.  So, for example, in this case
we have a position of 2 4 3, that is,
the light points towards 0
and is at x2, that is, to the right, and
4, that is, upwards, and 3, that is,
towards me, okay?  So
I do this.
We have turn signals and we have
this light.  If I tell you, for
example, that I want -4,
we will see how the light comes from below.
If I tell you that instead of 2 we want
-2,
the light comes from the left.
And if I tell him that instead of three
we want -3,
the light will come from behind.
The idea, once again, is that we get
used to the fact that at a given moment,
x is everything that happens on this
axis, y is everything that happens on this
axis.  This is like 2D, but the z is
everything that happens in depth, where
three, so positive means toward me
and negative means away from me,
right?  He walks away from me.
Once we've talked a little bit about
lights, we also need to talk a
little bit about materials.
Materials can be added to objects and with
materials come textures, so
materials
and I say for a moment
afame material simplest
blin orfón.
There are different shaders,
okay?
Okay.  And this,
okay?  This
together with the parameters.
Ah, light, no, sorry.
Okay, along with the
position, radius, color parameters,
and so on,
we have the ability to define
colors, right?  More precisely.  I'm going to
create a FF00 sphere,
okay?  And we have a red sphere with a
white specularity, right?  It's like
the object reflects white, but 015
specularity,
but specularity doesn't have to
be white.  I'm going to put, for example, an
object that is a bit pearly, let's say,
00 FF00.
That is, the object is red, but
it reflects light.  I don't know if there's a green light.   Just
a moment.
Speculate.  I am in speculation.
Specularity.  Okay, it should be
reflecting green.   It does
n't look very green, but hey,
whatever.  Okay.  And then the shininess,
which is the brightness.
A gloss of zero
means the material is matte.
Uh, no, it can't be.  It can't be
because I gave it a zero
and it's ignoring me.
Okay, no.  Mm.
Momentín,
eh,
specular
and shine
are not working at all.
Okay,
standard month.  Okay,
now yes.
Come on, this over here, this over here, this over
here.  Now yes.  Okay.
So,
metalness,
if I put 0.1 it's a plastic, okay?
If I put one it's a metal,
okay?  It is a metal.  If you look closely, it is
completely reflective.
Now, shininess or roughness, sorry.  If
I give it a zero
it's very bright.
If I put 0.5 it is rougher.  And if I
put one on it, it's a plastic object,
okay?  It is a completely
rough object, like a ping pong ball.
The idea, the idea, therefore, is that we
can create objects, we can add
lights to a certain extent, we can uh
add textures.
Next we are going to add textures
along with materials.  The
classic exercise, as you can imagine, is to
create a planet, a planet Earth.  So
let's go for it.
Uh, 017 textures.
Okay, let's see,
ad Earth texture.
For this I'm going to tell you that NASA Earth
Textures,
NASA, the NASA page has some
pretty cool textures.
So, I'm going to download some
texture, for example, this one.
Okay, this
is 5400,
well, 2 megabytes.  Okay, no need for
this.  Okay, let's download this
image.
Let's download this image.  I'm keeping
this image.  I save it in second, in
multimedia, in analysis, in
areas of specialization in exercises
like NASAr.jpg.
And now I come this way.  And now I come
this way,
okay?  And I go to 08
earth texture.
So basically we created an image.
It's literally an image tag.  And
the source and the source is NASAIra.jpg,
JPG,
textured sphere, where basically in
the material, instead of putting a color
we put a texture, right?
Earth texture,
earth texture earth texture metalness
0.2, rafness 1. Okay.  Okay.  Sky and
lights, no, no, we'll see this later, but
no.  Okay, so I'm coming this way.
earth texture.  Okay.  And if we look closely,
we will see that
the land is there.  Let's give the sun more stick
.  Skyer, okay?  I'm going to set Ambient 0.5
to zero, okay?  And I'm
going to change the sunlight to Intensity 10. Let's see what
happens.  Surcharge and pam.  There we have the
land there to death.  Okay, let's see.
Radius 3.
Okay, there's the big land.  Very good.
Since the Sun is behind you, it
cannot be seen.  Okay, so what
I'm going to do is tell you that the sun is
at +3.   Maybe
I've gone too far.  Eh, I'm going to say
zero so that it hits right
there, for example.
Now, next, by God, it's the
United States.  I wanted to see
Spain, but oh well, it's going to happen.  Okay,
there's Spain.  Moment.
Okay, I'm actually in Ecuador.
Okay, now what I want to do is
add cloud layers, okay?  It's because
I see the Earth in a cloud, without a single
cloud and it's not cool.  Just a moment, just a moment,
because something else I want to do is just
a moment.  Well, now I'll add clouds.
Uh, here the metalness, I'm going to say
rafness 0.5.
like the earth shines a
little, okay?  But of course, it
shines a little, because it's supposed to, it's
supposed to be all like little lies,
right?  But I go, I go, I go.  Luis, Luis, here
we go.  Okay, not the same
cinematic intro, but yeah, well, I don't know, no,
something that looks cool on screen and
is pure 3D and such.  Okay, so,
like I was saying, you see, you see that
the earth reflects the same thing.
the earth, okay?  That water and it is like it is
not supposed to be supposed to be that water
reflects more than the earth.  Okay.  Hey, I
come over here, I come over here and I say
add eh shininess, right?  So, uh,
roughness map.  And then on the Earth page
there are maps of this.  Well, this is
bacimetry, which isn't bad either.
Let's see, topography.
Yes, but
it's Ah, no, that's it.  Okay, so here goes
symmetry.  Okay, bacimetry.
I'm going to take this, which isn't
exactly what I want either.  Okay, let's see.
Nasa visible earth.  Hey,
damn it,
Rafnes.
M. let's say.
Okay.  Well, yes, for symmetry.
Okay, wait a minute.
Ah, wait, wait, wait.  Well, to
start I want this.  I want the
cloud map.   I
want this for sure.
I'm going to save it as NASA clouds.
Okay.  And
now, well, I'll have no
choice but to use the barometer map.
Wait a minute.  Wow.
So
I'm going to take it.  There's the
topography one.
Okay, I'll take it down, I'll take it
down.
And if things get tough, if things
get tough, what I can do is
roughness.
I can take
multimedia,
analysis, specialization, exercises,
roughness,
I take it to the desktop, I
open it with [ __ ]
and I'm going to do, uh, I
'm going to force a roughness map.
Okay, stay.  No, the rules.  Okay,
colors.
Ah, you don't saturation.
Saturation out.  Okay, now I shine.
Contrast.
Contrast up, brightness
up.  This is what I want.
Okay, like that.  And this is literally what
I want.  So I save it as
roughness.
Now I return roughness to the site.
Okay.
Okay.  And now,
okay.
Okay.
I'm going this way.
019 texture roughness
and we see that we loaded NASA roughness.
Well, roughness looks just like
roughness.  And then let's see, the
source is ground texture and rafness map
is ground roughness.  I'm not entirely sure
about this, but let's see.
We recharge.
That syntax doesn't sound familiar to me.  Ah, well yes,
well yes, but it's the other way around.  If you
look, what happens is that the earth
is very bright and the eh and the east the
sea is not, okay?  Obviously it is
the other way around, so the colors are inverted.
Wow, what happened?   Let's
see, colors.
Invest.
Let's see.  Ah, FX.  No, let's see.  Oh.
apply.  Okay, now yes,
invert colors.  Now I
save it,
I apply it, I
load it.
Now yes.  Okay, and we see that now
the sea is super bright,
maybe too much, in fact, okay?
and the earth is more diffuse.  Well
now if you want, for example, what we
can do is we're going to
raise the sea a little, that is, I'm
going to levels and without touching the land, let's
see, without touching the land, we're
not going to
go to brightness contrast.   We
turn up the brightness.  Okay.  Something like that.   We
overwrite roughness,
okay?
We dump it,
copy it and paste it.
We recharge.  V. This is something else.
This is already cooler.
Okay.  Hey, this, as I say, is starting to get
cool.   It
's starting to get cool now.  But I want
a cloud map,
okay?  I want a cloud map
above, which means that I
now go here to
texture, I go to 020 eh texture or
cloud sphere
and then I do this.  I want a second
sphere.
If this has a radius of 1.21.  Oh no,
sorry, this is position a radius of
three.  This is going to have a radius of 3.1,
okay?  Or 3.2.
And I'm going to take this material away from you for
now.  The material.  Well, yes, I take
the material away from him.  If we look at it now,
we will see that a
sphere has been placed above it that is blocking my
view.  Okay?  So now I want to,
right?  Already a roughness texture, now
I want a transparency texture.   Let's
go for it.   Let's
go for it.   Just
a moment to wrap things up here.
Okay,
okay.  And I say
this and I say, eh, I have a black.  Well,
a gray scale
map of clouds
for
eh for this for leches for
outer sphere
apply that map both as diffuse
and opacity
And next
what we're going to do is use a
cloud map, not only to paste the
clouds on top of the map, but to use
the darker colors as
transparency.
Let's see it.
Okay.  And okay,
021 transparency.
Okay.  Good.  Uh, roughness of the earth, clouds,
well, it's NASA clouds,
okay?  With which it applies it as an alpha
map and also applies it as here it
applies it as a color and as an alpha map.
Let's see it.
And if everything goes well.
One moment.   Let's
see if we're seeing the Earth.   I do
n't think so.
Okay, I'm going to do one thing because the
problem is that that hm map doesn't
really have alpha.  So one thing
I can do
is first I'll retrieve it from the cloud and
paste it here.  Next I open it in
[ __ ].  And when I open it in [ __ ],
when I open it in [ __ ], I'm going to call it
layer.
Alpha color transparency.  Black
turns it into transparency.
Okay,
I'm saving it not as JPG, but as
PNG, because JPG doesn't support
transparency.
Now, I'll give it back to you next.
Wait what is saving now.  I'll
take it back
to exercises.
And here I'm going to say nasanubes.png.   I
say this because he wants to
use it as an alpha map, but
honestly, it doesn't have alpha.  This
is something else, okay?  So
if you look closely, I don't know if you'll see it,
but there's like a layer of clouds
above the ground, right?  There's like a
layer of clouds over there.
Okay, more stuff, more stuff I want
next.  Well, I want the Earth to
spin, okay?  I want the Earth to spin
around an axis so it has a
little bit of animation.
The problem is in this case that, of
course, I can only
rotate one of the objects right now.  Let's see it.
Let's see this way.
and rotate earth
eh around
Z axis no Z axis no axis
constant animationlale
Here what we are going to do, as you will
see in a moment,
is to put in
the animation component
and a little bit apart from that now we will put
a lot more pressure on the sun here, okay?  And a
little bit of the idea, what I want 022 eh
animation earth.
In this case I'm making a mistake on
purpose, uh, I'm doing it on
purpose.  Now you will see.
Okay, animation land.  Ah, you jerk,
both of them encourage me.  Okay, both of them cheer me up.   It
has been automatically corrected for me.  I didn't
want this to happen,
okay?  Because I'm being animated by the earth
at one speed and the clouds at another,
which is fun.  Okay, it has an effect.   Behold.
Look, we're going to see,
here we have a rotation from 0 to 360
and the duration is 30 seconds, okay?
30,000 milliseconds, while in the
outer layer the rotation lasts twice as long,
lasting 60 seconds or what is the same,
60,000 milliseconds.
I'm going to do one thing.
I'm going to give the sunlight a
much greater intensity.
Wow, this is something else.  Good.  And now
next, well, I don't know what
material I'm telling you is the earth's metalness material
0.01.  Let's see.
Au.
Uh, and rafness 0.8.
Well, something like that, I don't know.  Okay, in
Aframe and in any 3D system,
technically objects can be
grouped using something called
hierarchies.
Sure, what's going on?  Well,
technically right now the sphere of the
Earth and the sphere of the clouds are
different spheres and really, although
the clouds may be a bit different, they
should be the same sphere.
So in this case, what I want to do
is the following.
Create empty,
animate empty rotation
and make both spheres
children
of empty.  Okay, now you'll see that one
thing I find amazing about a frame
is that in the same way that in HTML
we have child tags and we have
parent tags, in A frame we also
have that.  Let's see it.
Okay, this is 023 hierarchy.
And here we go.
Outer layer of clouds.  Here, if you
look closely, there is a label called Earth
Group.
which is an empty entity, okay?  It's not
a sphere, it's not a box, it's an
entity, it's a void.  But if you look closely, it
starts here, ends here, and within
this entity are the other two
entities, which means that just
like with pure HTML, these two
entities belong together.
Hey, okay, wait a second, they still
have animations.  I don't want this
animation.
What I want is for the two spheres to
go together.  Now yes, okay?  There.  And
then, obviously, if we want, we
can say, let's see it, we
can say, hey, wait a second,
that the animation should be much slower.
Okay, there.  Now it's like I was going
too fast.
Okay, okay, perfect.  It's pretty.
What could we be missing?  We may be missing
many things.
Well, apart from the fact that I can zoom in,
I can zoom out
and with this we can easily make a
spaceship game, okay?
in plan to explore.  Wait, I have
something stuck in my throat.
Okay,
let's see if uh and this is where I'm going to
get to the weak point, okay?  I'm going to
start
getting into the weak zone of frame by frame
to see if it lets me do something like
special effects, okay?  as
camera effects.
The special effects are, for
example, such as to make a glow.  Let's
see it.
Is there any
post process glow effect available?
I reckon he'll say no.  This is it,
okay?  Because Frame does not include
post-processing effects.  For that, the next
day we will go to a library
called 3.js.  Look, it's actually here.
Okay.  And we'll see.
Okay.  Okay.  Okay.
Option two.
This is stronger.  This is more for
the next day.  No, not this.
Okay, I don't know,
I'm just afraid this place won't
work.
We're going to say let's go with option
full code please.   I
always tend to make the map of the Earth
because the Earth's army because
with just a couple of spheres it looks
quite apparent, there's no need to model
many more things and eh, in a moment
with just a little bit you can do a
cool exercise.
Obviously what's coolest is bringing
objects,
let's say,
okay?  Modeling and making a 3D scene.
Let's see it.
I want, as I said, a
little bit of a
post-processing effect.
Let's see.
Au.
Good.  And having said that, once you're
thinking about this,
let's ask ourselves the question:
why can't
we do this from now on, not just to make a
map of the Earth, obviously, but
to make 3D websites?  That is,
instead of a website being 2D,
a website is a 3D space.  Okay.
Yeah, I think I think I can guess what it
is.  Just a moment.  Let's see it.
Let's see.
Yeah.  Yeah.
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
Okay, very good.
Well, this is what I mean.
[Music]
Wait, I'm going to
because I'm going deaf, huh?
Yes. I mean, it's a really
awesome website.  Okay, why not?  Look
what I do like this, it orbits and it's super
cool.
Why can't websites be made
like this?  Well, technically they can.  The thing is,
most people
understand the web as 2D, and as much as
we might like it, I can tell you that you can
imagine if you know a little about the
things I do, because I've been
waiting for years for this kind of thing to
become fashionable and for websites to
be much more interesting like
this one than they are up to this point.
But indeed, it seems
that things are difficult.   I'll take this
opportunity to tell you
that I'm just looking at this
project, which is clearly 2D, or rather, 3D,
sorry, because you can see the people
as if they were real geometry, or at least they
look like real geometry.  And I take this opportunity to
tell you that CSS has a part of
three-dimensionality.  Okay, now
you'll see.  I'm going to do this for a moment to
see if I don't have much hope, eh,
because eh 024
and eh post-processing I
don't have much hope, but let's
see.
Okay, yes, but not that strong.
Ah, look, actually, gee.  What a blast.
Well, he's gone too far, okay?
But let's see, I'm coming this way,
let's see, eh bloomold strength.  Well,
let's see a little bit,
okay?  And something that has a
little bit of shine, but that doesn't make us
go too far, okay?  Well,
something like that.  Well, I'll tell you.  It turns out
that CSS has a very
unknown part which is CSS 3D.  I'm going to give you
a demonstration that I think,
I hope, I suppose you'll like, which is
the following.  I'm coming over here and in the
next block we're going to put it
here in components
and uh
101 exercises,
okay?  In components I'm going to start by
creating 001 a grid of elements.html,
okay?  So I come over here and I say
create a
grid of elements on screen
as in a portfolio
all on screen and
1980 by or 1920 by 1080 okay.  Hey,
let's see.
Sorry,
pure HTML + CSS.  I say this because I haven't
told him.
And as you will now see, HTML and
CSS are languages ​​that are purely
2D, but it turns out that CSS has a part
that you will now see that can be combined
with JavaScript to make a little bit of
3D.  Now you'll see.
Okay, what we do in this case is
milk.
Well, I was going to tell you as simply as
possible, but it didn't work.
I'm going to close files.
Okay.
Okay.  A series of cards.  Very good.
Okay.  Let's go for it.  This
basically, as you will now see, without
much history.
Parent, the components, exercises,
grid, elements, okay?  And that's it.  Okay,
very good.  Okay, but now
next, now next
within each element, now
next
I want Okay.
Now use CSS 3D
eh
a perspective
as if camera is on side
bottom.
Okay.  And then now 002
camera
with perspective.
Good.  So it turns out there's a
property around here that's this one, right?
which is the property of perspective.  And the
perspective property along with
perspective origin allows us to
specify the angle at which
the camera is and the tilt, let's say.
Okay, so the vanishing point
.  Now you'll see.
Let's
see if they give you one.  There was a boy.
Okay,
okay.  I do this
and there is no camera perspective.  Okay,
and I do this
and this happens, okay?  And if you
notice,
not only, okay, not only does the camera
have perspective,
but the elements
have a kind of
forward and backward animation.
But now next, give me a
second, give me a second, I have
something.  Holy [ __ ],
okay.
Okay.
Give me a second, please.  Yeah.